Phi Beta Kappa; Records ua800.008
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Phi Beta Kappa, Alpha Alpha Chapter Records1940-1992
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Phi Beta Kappa. Alpha Alpha Chapter of New York (University at Albany)
ua800.008
1.2 cubic ft.
The Phi Beta Kappa, Alpha Alpha Chapter Records contain documents related to the formation and activities of the Alpha Alpha chapter of Phi Beta Kappa at the University at Albany.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted with the exception of select files noted below. Researchers seeking access to these materials should contact the head of Special Collections and Archives.
Biographical Sketch
Phi Beta Kappa is an academic honor society founded at the College of William and Mary in 1776, created to promote excellence in the liberal arts and sciences. Administration and faculty at the University at Albany applied several times for a chapter; in 1973 this application was finally approved, and the Alpha Alpha chapter of Phi Beta Kappa was formed.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of the Phi Beta Kappa, Alpha Alpha Chapter Records are in the form of memos, correspondence, reports, printed material, and notes related to the University’s applications to form a chapter of Phi Beta Kappa: first in 1950, again in 1970, and finally, successfully, in 1973. There are also similar materials on the formation of the Alpha Alpha chapter in 1973-1974 including the adoption of bylaws and installation ceremony. The rest of the records reflect the chapter’s later activities. Chief among these are memos and publicity surrounding the arrangements for a Phi Beta Kappa visiting scholar; information about the students selected to Phi Beta Kappa each year; and contracts, programs, and photographs of initiation ceremonies.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by the Alpha Alpha Chapter of Phi Beta Kappa. A further accession was received in August 2006
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Both series are arranged chronologically.
Greek letter societies; Learned institutions and societies; Initiations (into trades, societies, etc.); Albany (N.Y.); Contracts; Correspondence; Memorandums; Photographs; Programs (documents); Phi Beta Kappa; Phi Beta Kappa. Alpha Alpha of New York (State University of New York at Albany); State University of New York at Albany
- Application to Phi Beta Kappa, 1940-1974; Undated; 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes the various reports which the University at Albany submitted to the Phi Beta Kappa organization between 1950 and 1974, as well as the memorandums, correspondence, and notes related to the generation of those application materials. Also included are some printed materials about Phi Beta Kappa used as reference material during this process. This series also contains similar records relating to the establishment of the Alpha Alpha chapter once the application was accepted.
  - Handbook for new members, application materials, issue of Key Reporter, 1940-1973; Undated (Box 1 (1-Application to Phi Beta Kappa), Folder 1)
  - Preliminary Phi Beta Kappa application, 1967 (Box 1 (1-Application to Phi Beta Kappa), Folder 2)
  - Letter from Phi Beta Kappa Committee on Qualifications and instructions for general report, 1968 (Box 1 (1-Application to Phi Beta Kappa), Folder 3)
  - Completed 1968 Phi Beta Kappa application (Box 1 (1-Application to Phi Beta Kappa), Folder 4-6)
  - Memos, reports, and notes related to Phi Beta Kappa application, 1968-1970 (Box 1 (1-Application to Phi Beta Kappa), Folder 7)
  - Memos, notes, and correspondence related to Phi Beta Kappa application, formation, and selection of members, 1968-1974; Undated (Box 1 (1-Application to Phi Beta Kappa), Folder 8-9)
  - Updated supplement to Phi Beta Kappa application, 1969 (Box 2 (1-Application to Phi Beta Kappa), Folder 1)
  - Correspondence about Phi Beta Kappa application, 1970 (Box 2 (1-Application to Phi Beta Kappa), Folder 2)
  - Preliminary application to Phi Beta Kappa, 1970-1971 (Box 2 (1-Application to Phi Beta Kappa), Folder 3)
  - Memos and notes related to 1970-1971 Phi Beta Kappa application, Undated (Box 2 (1-Application to Phi Beta Kappa), Folder 4)
  - Completed Phi Beta Kappa application, 1971 (Box 2 (1-Application to Phi Beta Kappa), Folder 5-6)
  - Memos and notes related to 1971-1972 Phi Beta Kappa campus visit, Undated (Box 2 (1-Application to Phi Beta Kappa), Folder 7)
  - Memos, notes and correspondence related to Phi Beta Kappa application, 1971-1972; Undated (Box 2 (1-Application to Phi Beta Kappa), Folder 8-9)
  - Statement from SUNYA Phi Beta Kappa Committee to Phi Beta Kappa general meeting, 1973 (Box 2 (1-Application to Phi Beta Kappa), Folder 10)
  - Memo on approval of SUNYA Phi Beta Kappa application, 1973 (Box 2 (1-Application to Phi Beta Kappa), Folder 11)
  - Correspondence and memos related to installation and formation of Alpha Alpha chapter, 1973-1974; Undated (Box 2 (1-Application to Phi Beta Kappa), Folder 12)
- Alpha Alpha Chapter Activities, 1973-1992; Undated; 2
  This series contains documents related to the activities of the Alpha Alpha chapter of Phi Beta Kappa, beginning with its installation in 1974. It includes contracts and correspondence related to planning initiation dinners; programs and photographs from initiation dinners; and lists, correspondence, information cards and certificates relating to the selection of students for membership in Phi Beta Kappa.
  - Initiation programs; memos and correspondence related to chapter activity; clippings on Phi Beta Kappa bicentennial, 1973-1978; Undated (Box 3 (2-Alpha Alpha Chapter Activities), Folder 1)
  - Programs from Ceremony of Installation of Alpha Alpha Chapter, 1974 (Box 3 (2-Alpha Alpha Chapter Activities), Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Installation of Alpha Alpha Chapter, 1974 (Box 3 (2-Alpha Alpha Chapter Activities), Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Installation and memo from Arthur Ekrich, 1974 (Box 3 (2-Alpha Alpha Chapter Activities), Folder 4)
  - Installation invitations, 1974 (Box 3 (2-Alpha Alpha Chapter Activities), Folder 5)
  - Memos and notes related to member selection and initiation, 1975-1978 (Box 3 (2-Alpha Alpha Chapter Activities), Folder 6)
  - Reservation Contracts for Ballroom and Patroon Room, 1974-1979 (Box 3 (2-Alpha Alpha Chapter Activities), Folder 7)
  - Cards with selected student names and information, 1974-1984 (Card-file 1)
  - Photographs of initiation, 1975 (Box 3 (2-Alpha Alpha Chapter Activities), Folder 8)
  - Certificates for students who refused or did not respond to selection; mockup of 1979 initiation program, 1975-1976; 1979-1981; 1983-1984; Undated (Box 3 (2-Alpha Alpha Chapter Activities), Folder 9)
  - Phi Beta Kappa bulletin, 1976 (Box 3 (2-Alpha Alpha Chapter Activities), Folder 10)
  - Notices for Phi Beta Kappa dinners mailed by secretary, 1976-1979 (Box 3 (2-Alpha Alpha Chapter Activities), Folder 11)
  - Menus and catering contracts for Phi Beta Kappa dinners, 1976-1980 (Box 3 (2-Alpha Alpha Chapter Activities), Folder 12)
  - Correspondence related to Phi Beta Kappa dinners; dinner invitations to SUNYA president, 1977-1979; Undated (Box 3 (2-Alpha Alpha Chapter Activities), Folder 13)
  - Notes and memos related to member selection-[RESTRICTED], 1977-1979; Undated (Box 3 (2-Alpha Alpha Chapter Activities), Folder 14)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Must consult archivist before viewing this material.
  - Originals of initiation programs, 1977-1979; Undated (Box 3 (2-Alpha Alpha Chapter Activities), Folder 15)
  - Initiation programs, 1977-1990 (Box 3 (2-Alpha Alpha Chapter Activities), Folder 16)
  - Notes, working papers related to Phi Beta Kappa, 1978-1979; Undated (Box 3 (2-Alpha Alpha Chapter Activities), Folder 17)
  - Phi Beta Kappa dinner procedures, 1979; Undated (Box 3 (2-Alpha Alpha Chapter Activities), Folder 18)
  - Memo relating to Phi Beta Kappa, 1980 (Box 3 (2-Alpha Alpha Chapter Activities), Folder 19)
  - Memos, correspondence, publicity materials related to Phi Beta Kappa visiting scholar Malcolm Kerr, 1981; Undated (Box 3 (2-Alpha Alpha Chapter Activities), Folder 20)
  - Memo related to initiation banquet, 1982 (Box 3 (2-Alpha Alpha Chapter Activities), Folder 21)
  - Notes and memos related to member selection-[RESTRICTED], 1982-1983; Undated (Box 3 (2-Alpha Alpha Chapter Activities), Folder 22)
  - Cards with selected student names and information, 1985-1992 (Card-file 2)